<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed>
    <entry>
        <title>Reboot my personal blog</title>
        <updated>2024-08-24T14:57:00Z</updated>
        <summary>
            This post introduces the reboot of my personal blog, I will explain the reasons and the topics which you can
            expect in the future.
        </summary>
        <category term="meta" />
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<p>With this post I like to reboot my personal blog. In the past I have used for a long time
<a href="https://medium.com/@chriskapp">medium.com</a> as blogging platform but there are several reasons why I am
no longer happy with the platform. I have thought about choosing one of the thousand alternative platforms for blogging
but in the end they all have downsides. Instead of going through all downsides I like to share my thoughts about the
advantages of a self-hosted blog, maybe I can convince also some readers to start again with a self-hosted blog.</p>

<h2>Data sovereignty</h2>

<p>If you host your own blog the content of your blog is under your control. An external blogging platform is a company
which needs to make money, they need to somehow use your blogging content to create revenue since they offer the platform
mostly for free. This is done by adding some kind of partner program or paywalls. On your own blog you are complete free
from those topics and you can get sure that your content is not misused.</p>

<h2>Data durability</h2>

<p>Your thoughts and ideas which you write are an important part of your legacy. You probably want that this content
is also available after your lifetime. Blogging platforms are limited to the lifetime of the company behind the platform
which is often not too long, if the company closes your content will also disappear. If you host your own blog you
have automatically multiple mechanisms to archive your content. In my case I use a public GitHub
<a href="https://github.com/chriskapp/personal-website/blob/main/resources/blog.xml">repository</a> where all
posts are stored. Then your blog is probably also covered by <a href="https://archive.org/">archive.org</a> which
creates over time a complete backup of your blog. Through your own domain and content you basically participate in the
history of the internet.</p>

<h2>Data quality</h2>

<p>Most blogging platforms provide some kind of <abbr title="What You See Is What You Ge">WYSIWYG</abbr> editor to write
your content. Such editors often produce ugly HTML and they are also limited. Especially for development content I find
often examples where code examples or code-highlighting are broken. If you want to preserve your content for the long term
it is probably better to write the HTML content by your self, this ensures better data quality and makes it better readable.</p>

<h2>Decentralization</h2>

<p>This is an idealistic point but if you host your own blog you help to decentralize the web. You may know
the largest problem of the current web is centralization, this means that there are only some centralized platforms or
so called data silos like Twitter, Facebook etc. where all content gets created. In the end those platforms are dependent
on your content, if you decide to move this content to your own blog you remove some power from those platforms.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>These points have convinced me to start again with my own self-hosted blog. But there are of course also some
disadvantages. The largest disadvantage is probably discoverability, on a central platform you get
automatically readers from the users on the platform, on your own blog you depend on a search engine to find
new readers. In the future it would be cool to have some kind of aggregation service where self-hosted blogs could
register to reach a wider audience, to support those self-hosted blogs.</p>

<h2>Future</h2>

<p>Regarding this blog, in the future I will write content around my open source projects and in general development topics like API management,
REST, code generation, specifications and decentralization. I will also go through my old <a href="https://chriskapp.medium.com/">medium.com</a>
posts and transfer them to this blog. If you are interested feel free to subscribe to the <a href="https://chrisk.app/feed">feed</a>.

]]></content>
    </entry>
</feed>
